Guide to the George M.P. Baird Papers, ca. 1915-ca. 1960 CTC.1970.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
George M.P. Baird Papers
ca. 1915-ca. 1960
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Baird, George M. P. (George Mahaffey Patterson)
CTC.1970.01
10.5 Linear Feet (21 boxes, 387 folders, 282 slides)
CONTENT WARNING -- This finding aid contains records that have been identified as including offensive, harmful, racist, or misrepresentative creator supplied language. In keeping with archival best practice, this language has been retained to preserve the context of the records. In keeping but acknowledging this language, A&SC hopes to encourage critical assessment and questioning of historical materials. Researchers should bear this in mind when accessing. This collection contains the papers, news clippings, and slides relating to lectures on the performing arts presented by George M. Baird. Baird was an English professor at the University of Pittsburgh from 1908-1961.
Biography
George M.P. Baird, 1887-1970, B.A. University of Pittsburgh, 1909, made varied and lasting contributions to the University. He wrote the lyrics of the Alma Mater, suggested the Panthers as the name of the football team, and was actively associated with the Scottish Room Committee. He left his teaching position at Pitt for the Army in 1917. Upon his return, he began a new career in government service in the city of Pittsburgh and was senior research analyst for the Department of City Planning when he retired in 1961. Throughout his life he maintained a strong interest in the theatre. He wrote and produced several one-act plays, directed, served as a theatre consultant, and lectured on the theatre.
Scope and Content Notes
The clippings file is presently maintained largely as Mr. Baird had originally maintained it, although a new classification, "Names", has been added and some subject headings have been combined. Mr. Baird's headings and spelling have been retained on new folders, but in some cases revised in the inventory list following, for reasons of consistency, clarity and conformity. Included with the clippings are Mr. Baird's notes, papers and lectures.
Arrangement
Series I. Clippings and Papers
Series II. Lantern Slides
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Estate of George M. P. Baird in 1970.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Boxes 18-21 contain lantern slides.
Previous Citation
George M.P. Baird Papers, ca. 1915-1960, CTC.1970.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Papers of George M. P. Baird, ca. 1915-1960, CTC.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Drama, Medieval -- Pictorial works; Greek drama -- Pictorial works; Theater; Performing arts; Dance -- History; Theater -- United States -- History; Pittsburgh (Pa.); European drama -- Renaissance, 1450-1600; Drama -- Origin -- Pictorial works; Baird, George M. P. (George Mahaffey Patterson); University of Pittsburgh
- Clippings and Papers, I.
  Scope and Contents note
  The clippings file is presently maintained largely as Mr. Baird had it, although a new classification, Names, has been added and some subject headings have been combined. Mr. Baird's headings and spelling have been retained on new folders, but in some cases revised in the inventory list following, for reasons of consistency, clarity and conformity. Included with the clippings are Mr. Baird's notes, papers and lectures. There are nine subseries represented in their original order: Names, Shakespeare, Dance, Drama Topics, Drama Regions, Music, Stage, Theatre, and George M. Baird Productions and Publications.
  - Names, 1.
    - Abbey Theatre (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Actors Studio. Stanislavsky. The Method (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American National Theatre and Academy (ANTA) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, Maxwell (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Andreyev, Leonid (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ballet Russe. Diaghilev (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Barrie, Sir James (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Beggar's Opera (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Belasco, David (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bjorson, Bjorstjerne (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brieuz, Eugene (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cauve-Souris (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chekhov, Anton (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - City Center Theatre (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Civic Repertory Theatre (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Claudel, Paul (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Comedie Francais (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Craig, Gordon (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - D'Annunzio, Gabriele (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dunsany, Lord (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Eliot, T.S (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Federal Theatre Project. W.P.A. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Foster, Stephen G. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Galsworthy, John (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Gilbert and Sullivan (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Grand Guignol (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Group Theatre (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Green Pastures (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Sacha Guiltry (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hauptmann, Gerhart (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ibsen and Ibsenism (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Jones, Robert Edmond (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Jonson, Ben (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Library Theatre (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Maeterlinck, Maurice (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Malvery Festival (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Marlowe, Christopher (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Masefield, John (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Mercury Theatre (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miller, Arthur (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Moliere (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Molnar, Ferenc (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Moscow Art Theatre (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Moscow Art Theatre: Musical Studio (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - O'Casey, Sean (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - O'Neill, Eugene (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Phoenix Theatre (Off-Broadway) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - One-Act Repertory Company (New York) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Pirandello, Luigi (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Playwrights-- Company (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Portmanteau Theatre. Stuart Walker (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Reinhardt, Max (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Rostand, Edmond (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Sartre, Jean-Paul (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Schnitzler, Arthur (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Shaw, George Bernard (Box 3, Folder 08-10)
    - Shaw, George Bernard: Portraits and scenes (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sherwood, Robert E. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Strindberg, August (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Synge, John M. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Theatre Arts Magazine (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Theatre Guild (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Tobacco Road (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Uncle Tom's Cabin (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Urban, Joseph (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Verhaeren, Emile (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Vieux-Colombier and Jacques Copeau (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Wilder, Thornton (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Williams, Tennessee (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Yeats, William Butler (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Shakespeare, 2.
    - Actors (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Age and England (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Artist, thinker, craftsman (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Baird lectures (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bibliography (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Biography (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Characters (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Comedies (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Contemporaries (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Controversies: Problems and controversies (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Controversies: Lunatics, pretenders, and anti-Avonians (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Critics, commentators, editors, adapters (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Festivals, academic, non-commercials productions, etc. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Festivals: Stratford, Conn. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Festivals: Stratford, Ont. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Histories (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Libraries and collections (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Philosophy (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Portraits (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Productions: Cinema, TV (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Productions: Opera, musical comedy, ballet (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Productions: American: Modern (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Productions: Foreign: Modern (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford on Avon) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Shakespeare Newsletter (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Theatre: Shakespeare's physical stage and theatre (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Theatres: British: Modern (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Tragedies (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Tragedies: Hamlet (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Unclassified (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Dance, 3.
    - Aesthetic (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Ballet: Traditional (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Ballet: American (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Ballet: British and European (other than Russian) (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Ballet: Ruddian (other than Ballet Russe) (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Folk dance (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Folk dance: African (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Folk dance: American and Amerind (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Folk dance: British and European (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Folk dance: Latin American (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Folk dance: Oriental and South Seas (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - History and theory (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Oriental dance drama (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous and unclassified (Box 6, Folder 8)
      The lecture materials in box 6 folder 18 correspond to the collection of slides that are in Series II.
  - Drama Topics, 4.
    - Aesthetics of the drama (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Comedy and the comic spirit (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Closet drama (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Critics and criticism (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Expressionism as dramatic philosophy (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Farce (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - History: Baird lectures (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - History: Baird lectures: Working materials (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - History: Baird lectures: Evolution of drama (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - History: Baird lectures: Evolution of drama: notes (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Literary aspects (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Masque (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Medicine and psychopathology in relation to the drama (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Melodrama (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Miracle, morality, and liturgical drama: Medieval (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Miracle, morality plays: Modern. Oberammergau (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Monodrama (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Philosophy (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Plagiarism (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Play writing (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Plays: Modern: Abstracts (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Plays: One-act (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Primitive drama and ritual and dance (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Proletarian drama (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Propaganda in the theatre (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Propaganda: Peace plays (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Psychology of drama (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Realism (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Religious aspects (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Romanticism in drama (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Social function of drama (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Tragedy and the tragic spirit (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Unclassified (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Drama Regions, 5.
    - American (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - American, 1900-1950 (Box 8, Folder 8-14)
    - American, 1951-1957 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - American: Afro-American (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - American: Regional (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - American: Verse (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Australian (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Austrian: to 1938 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Austrian: Post WWII (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Balkan (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - British: Tudor (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - British: Restoration period and revivals (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - British: 18th century and revivals (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - British:19th century (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - British, 1850-1956 (Box 9, Folder 14-20)
    - British: Verse: 19th and 20th centuries (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Chinese (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Czechoslovakian: Pre-Communist (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Canadian (includes theatre) (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Dutch (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - European (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - European drama in the U.S. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - French: 17th century (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - French: 18th century (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - French: 19th century (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - French, 1900-1957 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
    - German: 18th, 19th century (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - German, 1900-1933 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - German: Nazi (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - German, 1946-1954 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - German dramatists in exile: 1933- (includes Austrian) (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Greek: Classic (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Greek: Modern: Productions and revivals (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Hungarian (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Icelandic (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Indian (Vedic, Hindu) (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Irish (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Israeli (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Italian: Commedia dell'Arte (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Italian: 17th-20th centuries (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
    - Japanese (includes lecture notes) (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Japanese, and dance drama of Bali (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Latin (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Norwegian (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Polish (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Russian: Pre-revolution (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Russian: Post-revolution (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Scottish (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Siamese (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Spanish: Pre-19th, 19th, and 20th, centuries (Box 11, Folder 18-19)
    - Spanish American (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Swedish and Danish (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Turkish (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Yiddish (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Music, 6.
    - Chanteurs and chanteuses (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Christmas carols (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Comic opera (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Composers: Classical (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Composer's Modernist (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Folk song: African (includes Africans Dutch) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Folk song: American: General and historic (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Folk song: American: Amerind (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Folk song: American: Chanteys, cowboys, work songs (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Folk song: American: Mountain ballads (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Folk song: American: Negro and spirituals (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Folk song: Asiatic (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Folk song: British (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Folk song: European (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - General (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Grand Opera (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Musical comedy and reviews, to 1945 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Musical comedy and reviews, 1945-1955 (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
    - Philosophy and Aesthetics (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Songs and songwriters: American (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Symphonic and chamber music (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Stage, 7.
    - Constructivism (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Craftsmen (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Décor (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Décor: American (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Décor: Foreign (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Design in communal buildings: Baird paper (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Ensemble and grouping (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Equipment (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Expressionism as stage technique (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Illusion, devices, and effects other than lighting (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Light control for theatres (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Make-up and character (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Lighting (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Properties (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Sets, ideas (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Stagecraft (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Theatre, 8.
    - Actors and actresses (Box 13, Folder 11-13)
    - Actors and actresses (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Actors: Training of (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Architecture (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Architecture: Ground plans (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Architecture: Stage (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Art theatre (See also Little theatres) (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Art theatre: American (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Art theatre: European (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Audiences (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Backstage, rehearsals, etc. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Buildings: Commercial (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Burlesque (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Censorship (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Children's theatre (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Circus (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Clowns, fools, zanies (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - College and university theatre (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Community theatre (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Diction and voice (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Direction and directors (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Economics of the theatre (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Entertainers (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Experimental theatre (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Experimental, non-commercial, art theatre: New York: Post, -1940 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Folk festivals, carnavals, rituals, parades, pageantry (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Harlequinade (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - History: Evolution of the physical theatre (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - History: Decay of the theatre (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - History: Decay of the theatre: Woes and jeremiads (includes notes) (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - History: Renaissance of the theatre (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Jargon, technical terms, slang (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Libraries and museums (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Little theatres (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Little theatres: Off-Broadway (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Marionettes and puppets (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Masks (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Minstrel shows: American (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Models. Sculptures (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Movies (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Novelties and freaks (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Open air theatre (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Pageantry (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Pantomime (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Pantomime: British and Continental (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Production and producers (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Radio (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Repertory theatres (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Revivals (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Revivals: Central City, Col. (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Royalties (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Showboats. Medicine shows (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Spectacle (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Stock companies (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Strolling companies (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Summer theatre (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Television (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Theatre in the round. Arena Theatre (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Theatres: History (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Theories and surveys (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Touring companies (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Traditions, customs, superstitions (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Vaudeville (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Wartime theatre (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Theatre: British "National Theatre" (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Theatre: Greek (includes Baird notes) (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Theatre: Malay, Chinese (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Unclassified (Box 17, Folder 12)
      One item from folder 13 titled Easter Miracle Drawing was oversized and moved to Curtis O/Miscellaneous 8.
  - George M. Baird Productions and Publications, 9.
    - Productions: Correspondence, clippings, etc. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Prose publications (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Unpublished manuscript (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Verse publications (Box 17, Folder 16)
- Lantern Slides, II.
  This series contains lantern slides utilized by George M. Baird in his lectures on theatre history and production. See Box 6, folder 18 for the lecture notes that correspond to these slides.
  - Evolution of drama (Box 18, Slide 1-4)
  - Primitive drama (Box 18, Slide 5-20)
  - Greek drama (Box 18, Slide 21-42)
  - Hellenistic, Greco-Roman, Roman theatre (Box 18, Slide 43-50)
  - Modern Greek theatre (Box 18, Slide 51-53)
  - Strolling players (Box 18, Slide 53-58)
  - Medieval drama (Box 18, Slide 59-75)
  - Tudor Theatre, Shakespeare (Box 19, Slide 1-28)
  - Tudor Theatre, Shakespeare -- Renaissance theatre (Box 19, Slide 29)
  - Court masque (Box 19, Slide 30-36)
  - Continental theatres: 16th-18th centuries (Box 19, Slide 37-54)
  - British theatre: 16th-19th (Box 19, Slide 55-72)
  - British theatre: 16th-19th -- Commedia dell'arte (Box 19, Slide 73)
  - French classic theatre (Box 20, Slide 1-3)
  - French classic theatre -- Stage lighting and mechanics (Box 20, Slide 4)
  - French classic theatre -- 19th century drama and stage (Box 20, Slide 5)
  - French classic theatre -- Stage design: 20th century (Box 20, Slide 6)
  - Art theatre (Box 20, Slide 7-14)
  - Multiple unit and revolving stages (Box 20, Slide 15-26)
  - Realism and naturalism (Box 21, Slide 1-3)
  - Stylization (Box 21, Slide 4-8)
  - Theatre slides (not arranged) (Box 21, Slide 9-27)
  - Misc. slides (non-theatrical) (Box 21, Slide 28-48)
  - Slides in preparation (Box 21, Slide 48-53)